Guide to the Segregation Photoprints MS 042
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Segregation Photoprints
1860-1972
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Library of Congress.
MS 042
0.5 Linear Feet, 1 box
This collection is comprised of black-and-white, 8 x 10" photoprints most presumably ordered from the Library of Congress in 1972. Most of the images are part of the Farm Security Administration-Office of War Information Collection and show African Americans in urban and rural settings during the Great Depression and World War II. Many of the images are available digitally from the American Memory collection at the Library of Congress: http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/fsahtml/fahome.html. The collection also includes some presumably original photography and pre-Civil War and reconstruction images.
Provenance
Provenance is unknown. The collection was found in storage under the Haas Library in 2007 and had been assembled in 1972. It was either ordered by a faculty member and given to the library or ordered by the library to support a course offered.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Farm Security Administration was an agency created in the New Deal. One of its missions was to photographically document the plight of rural/agrarian America. Similarly, the Office of War Information also had as one of its missions to photographically document life in wartime America. However, OWI's purpose was propagandistic and the FSA's documentary.
Sources:
FSA-OWI: About the Collection. Library of Congress. [http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/fsahtml/fabout.html].
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 150, 8 x 10", black and white photoprints. Most of the images are from Farm Security Administration-Office of War Information Collection at the Library of Congress. Images show African Americans in urban and rural settings during the Great Depression and World War II. Many of the images are available digitally from the American Memory collection at the Library of Congress: http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/fsahtml/fahome.html. The collection also includes some presumably original photography from the 1970s and pre-Civil War and reconstruction images.
Images are arranged generally by subject matter and include captions and LC item numbers. Separtion sheets with captions remain with photos, though, most contain the same information on the back side of the photo. Some other documentation that was found with this collection is included.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
Miscellaneous.
FSA-OWI: Depression/WWII Era Images of Segregated Black America
Children.; Small towns -- llinois.; African Americans; Photographs.; Documentary photography -- United States.; Racism -- United States; Great Depression.; Lee, Russell, 1903-1986.; Lange, Dorothea.; Delano, Jack.; Walcott, Marion Post.; United States. Office of War Information.; United States. Farm Security Administration.; Stryker, Roy Emerson, 1893-1975.; Siegel, Arthur S.
- Miscellaneous
  - Collection documentation, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Slavery and Reconstruction, 1866-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    General note
    Includes: "The Picture of a Negro Worker" [1903, Davidson, E.J.] LC# 54476/23887
    "An old time Charleston 'Mommer' and her charge in Charleston, South Carolina" [1899, Tarbell] LC# 54476/26366
    "Happy Family" - Harpers Weekly engraving, 1866 LC# 54476/38843
    Currier and Ives lithograph "Colored Beauty", 1877 LC# 54476/35745
    "Negro Life in the South" Harper's Weekly engraving, 1872 LC# 54476/18096
    4 Young Men - entitled "Four of a Kind", 1927 LC# 54476/38197
  - 1969 Yonkers teachers and students (Box 1, Folder 3)
    5 images, white teachers with African American students. Perhaps original photographs.
- FSA-OWI - Depression/WWII Era Images of Segregated Black America
  Scope and Contents note
  Incudes photographs by Russel Lee, Marion Post Walcott, Jack Delano, Arthur Siegel
  - Families, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Children, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Children, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chicago, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Detroit, 1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American South, 1930-1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)